Call me Ishmael.
叫我以赛马利
Some years ago,
having little or no money...
几年前我几乎身无分文……
I thought I would sail about
and see the oceans of the world.
我想我应该出海去看看世界
Whenever I get grim and spleenful...
当我心情沮丧脾气糟糕的时候……
whenever I feel like
knocking people 's hats off in the street...
当我看街上的人都不顺眼的时候……
whenever it's a damp,
drizzly November in my soul...
当我的心里像潮湿多雨的11月的时候……
I know that it's high time
to get to sea again.
我知道又到了立刻出海的时候了
Choose any path you please...
随意选一条航线……
and ten to one,
it carries you down to water.
十有八九它会把你带到水里
There 's a magic in water
that draws all men away from the land...
海水有一种魔力，可以吸引所有的男人们离开陆地……
Leads them over the hills down creeks,
and streams, and rivers to the sea.
引领他们越过山川,小溪,山涧与河流,最终到达大海
The sea...
面对大海……
where each man, as in a mirror,
finds himself.
每个男人都可以像照镜子一样，找回自我
And so it was
I duly arrived at the town of New Bedford...
确实如此，1841年的一个风雨交加的周六晚上
on a stormy Saturday late in the year 184 1.
我按时来到了新贝德福德这个小镇…
-Rum. 朗姆酒
-Rum it is. What mark? 朗姆酒是吧，用哪种喝法？
To this a penny, to that another penny, and so on to the top of the glass.
到这是一便士 到这是两便士 就这样直到杯子倒满
The Cape Horn measure, which
you may drink down for a full shilling.
如果用合恩角的喝法，你可以一先令一先令地喝
The penny mark. Nay, the full shilling.
便士记号， 不，来一先令的
You'll be wanting a room tonight.
你今晚需要个房间吧
You ain't no objections to sharing
a harpooneer's bed with him, have you?
你对和鱼叉手共睡一张床没有意见吧？
-You going whaling?  你是去捕鲸吗？
-That is my intention.  有这个打算
You need permission. You weren't born and bred in New Bedford,
were you?
你需要许可证，你不是在新贝德福德出生长大的吧？
No, I'm a stranger here.
不是，我是个外地人
-Then you'll have to have permission.  那你需要许可证
-Permission?   许可证？
Aye. From us, the men of New Bedford.
The sea is ours.
是的。由我们新贝德福德的人颁发的许可证
这片海是我们的。
Other seamen only have
a right of way through it.
其他海员水手只有通过的权利。
And the whale is ours. Ours alone.
鲸鱼也是我们的，只属于我们
No one else may hunt it down and kill it,
unless we say so.
除非我们允许，否则没人可以进行捕猎
Do you dispute that?
你对此有异议吗？
-I do not.  没有
-Good. 很好
Then you have our permission
to sail our sea.
那你就被允许在我们的海域航行了
Drink to this boy, mates?
伙计们，为这孩子干一杯？
Big whales to you, mate!
祝你捕到大鲸鱼，伙计！
Can whales do that?
鲸鱼有那么厉害？
Why, bless me, whales can do anything!
什么，保佑我吧，鲸鱼可什么都干得出来！
A whale can jump up like an earthquake...
鲸鱼跃出海面的时候就像地震一样……
and come down on you like
a mountain that's somehow put to sea.
然后像大山坠入海中一样扑向你
A whale can stave in the ribs
of the biggest ships...
鲸鱼可以撞扁最大型的渔船的龙骨……
swallow whole crews,
pick its teeth with the oars.
吞掉所有船员，再用船桨来剔牙
Mind, lad, if God ever wanted to be a fish,
he'd be a whale.
听着，小伙子，如果上帝要变成一条鱼的话，一定会是条鲸鱼
Believe that, he'd be a whale.
相信我，他会是条鲸鱼
Ahab.
亚哈
Who's Ahab?
谁是亚哈？
Captain Ahab to you.
你应该叫亚哈船长
-Who's Captain Ahab? 谁是亚哈船长？
-Aye. 啊
Ahab's Ahab.
亚哈就是亚哈
Music.
奏乐
In Amsterdam there lived a maid
在阿姆斯特丹住着一个女佣
And she was mistress of her trade
她是这一行的女主人
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我不再跟你四处流浪，漂亮姑娘
A-roving, a-roving
四处流浪，四处流浪
Sing!
一起唱！
Since roving's been my ruin
自从流浪毁了我
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我不再跟你四处流浪，漂亮姑娘
Her cheeks were red, her eyes were brown
她的脸颊红红的，眼睛是棕色的
Mark well what I do say
记住我所说的话
Her cheeks were red, her eyes were brown
她的脸颊红红的，眼睛是棕色的
Her curly hair was hanging down
她的卷发垂了下来
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我不再跟你四处流浪，漂亮的姑娘
A-roving, a-roving
四处流浪，四处流浪
Since roving's been my ruin
自从流浪毁了我
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我不再跟你四处流浪，漂亮的姑娘
Landlord, which is the harpooneer
I'm to sleep with tonight?
老板，哪位是今晚和我一起睡的鱼叉手？
He ain't among them.
他不在这里
He's what you might call a dark-complexioned
chap.
他是个你们称为黑皮肤的家伙
He'll be along
as soon as he finishes selling his head.
他一旦把他那些人头卖出去就会来的
-His what? 他的什么？
-Selling his head. 卖他的人头
Though he may have some difficulty
in getting rid of it.
虽然他可能不太容易出手
New Bedford's overstocked.
新贝德福德的库存太多了
-With what? 什么库存太多了？
-Heads, of course!  当然是人头太多了！
Come on, lad.
过来，小伙子
Mark well what I do say
好好记住我说的话
I kissed her once, I kissed her twice
我亲了她一下，我亲了她两下
And found she was as cold as ice
发现她的身体冰凉
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我再也不跟你四处流浪，漂亮的姑娘
A-roving, a-roving
四处流浪，四处流浪
Since roving's been my ruin
自从流浪毁了我
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我再也不跟你四处流浪，漂亮的姑娘
Now, the young maid was fancy-free
Mark well what I do say
如今年轻的美人自由了，好好记住我说的话
The young maid was fancy-free If I could take her home with me
年轻的女仆无忧无虑 如果我能把她带回家
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我再也不跟你去流浪，漂亮的姑娘
A-roving, a-roving
四处流浪，四处流浪
Since roving's been my ruin
自从流浪毁了我
I'll go no more a-roving with you, fair maid
我再也不跟你去流浪，漂亮的姑娘
-Wait. Hold on. 等等，别动
-Who the devil are you?  你到底是谁？
Who no speak? I kill you!
不说话是吗？ 小心我杀了你！
Landlord!
老板！
Peter Coffin! Coffin, save me!
Peter Coffin！
彼得.考芬 救救我！
Now, now, now.
来了，来了
What is all this about?
这是怎么回事？
Why didn't you tell me
I was sleeping with a cannibal?
你怎么没告诉我要和一个食人族一起睡？
I thought you knowed.
我以为你知道的
Didn't I tell you
he was around the town selling heads?
我没告诉你他在这阵子附近卖人头吗？
Landlord, tell him to stash that tomahawk,
or pipe, or whatever you call it.
老板，让他把那个战斧还是烟斗什么的玩意收好
Well, pleasant dreams.
好的，晚安
Better a sober cannibal
than a drunken Christian.
一个清醒的食人族好过一个烂醉的基督徒
In this same New Bedford,
there stands a Whaleman 's Chapel...
就在这个新贝德福德镇上， 有一个属于捕鲸者的小教堂……
and few are the fishermen shortly bound for the Indian Ocean or Pacific...
那些短期内出发前往印度洋的渔民们……
who fail to visit there.
几乎没有人不去那里
The will of God I did deny
我否认了上帝的旨意
And so my sacred duty fled
逃避了我神圣的职责
Oh, my Lord's awful penalty
哦，上帝的惩罚太可怕了
Is not to die and yet be dead
不仅是死去和等死
The ribs and terrors in the whale
鲸鱼的肋骨和恐怖
Arched over me a dismal gloom
在我身上形成了阴森的阴影
While all God's sun-lit waves rolled by
当所有上帝照耀的波浪滚滚而过
And lift me deepening down to doom
把我带到更深的厄运之中
I saw the opening maw of hell
我看到地狱之门打开
With endless pains and sorrows there
那里有无尽的痛苦和悲伤
Which none but they that feel can tell
只有经历过的人才能描述
Oh, I was plunging to despair
哦，正当我要陷入绝望之中
In black distress, I called my God
在黑暗的痛苦中，我呼唤我的上帝
When I could scarce believe him mine
当我几乎不能相信他的时候
He bowed his ear to my complaints
他侧耳倾听了我的抱怨
No more the whale
我不要再把
Did me confine
鲸鱼关起来
Amen
阿门
"And God had prepared a great fish...
“上帝安排了一条大鱼……
"to swallow up Jonah."
要吞掉约拿“
Shipmates...
船友们……
the sin of Jonah...
约拿的罪
was in his disobedience of the command of God.
是他不顺服从神的旨意
He found it a hard command.
他觉得这命令太难了
And it was, shipmates...
是的，船友们……
for all the things that God would have us do are hard.
因为神要我们做的一切事都是难的
If we would obey God, we must disobey ourselves.
我们若要顺服神，就必须违背自己。
But Jonah still further flouts at God by seeking to flee
from him.
可是约拿试图逃跑，这是对上帝的进一步不敬
Jonah thinks that a ship made by men...
约拿以为人类造的船
will carry him into countries where God does not reign.
会把他带到没有上帝统治的国度
He prowls among the shipping...
他在船只之间徘徊……
Like a vile burglar,
hastening to cross the seas.
像一个卑鄙的窃贼一样，急着要出海
And as he comes aboard,
the sailors mark him.
当他上船时，水手们在他身上做记号
The ship puts out...
船出发了
but soon the sea rebels.
It will not bear the wicked burden.
但是很快大海反抗了起来，它不能容忍这个邪恶的负担
A dreadful storm comes up.
The ship is like to break.
一场可怕的暴风雨来了，而船好像就要沉了
The boatswain calls
all hands to lighten her.
水手长发动所有人来减轻船的重量
Boxes, bales, and jars are clattering
overboard.
箱子，包裹，和罐子被稀里哗啦的地到海里
The wind is shrieking. The men are yelling.
狂风在咆哮，人们在尖叫
"l fear the Lord," cries Jonah...
“我敬畏上帝”，约拿喊道
"the God of heaven,
who hath made the sea and the dry land."
“天上的神，他创造了大海和旱地”
Again, the sailors mark him.
水手们又给他做了记号
But wretched Jonah cries out to them
to cast him overboard...
但是可怜的约拿呼喊着要他们把他扔到海里
for he knew that for his sake
this great tempest was upon them.
因为他知道这场风暴是冲着他来的
Now behold Jonah...
现在看看约拿啊……
taken up as an anchor
and dropped into the sea...
被当做锚丢到海里……
into the dreadful jaws awaiting him.
丢到等待已久的血盆大口之中
And the great whale shoots
to all his ivory teeth...
而鲸鱼竖起它象牙般的利齿
Like so many white bolts upon his prison.
就像牢房里到处都是的白色栅栏
And Jonah cries unto the Lord...
约拿在鱼腹中
out of the fish's belly.
求告耶和华
Nut observe his prayer, shipmates.
但是请注意他的祈祷，船友们。
He doesn't weep and wail.
他没有哭泣或悲叹
He feels his punishment is just.
He leaves deliverance to God.
他觉得对他的惩罚是公正的，他把自己交给上帝处置
And even out of the belly of hell...
甚至是在地狱的肚子里
grounded upon the ocean's utmost bones...
大海的最深处
God heard him when he cried.
上帝还是听到了他的喊叫
And God spake unto the whale.
上帝对鲸鱼做了吩咐
And from the shuddering cold
and blackness of the deep...
鲸鱼突然从深海的冰冷和黑暗之中
the whale breached into the sun...
冲到了阳光下……
and vomited out Jonah upon the dry land.
把约拿吐出来落到了陆地上
And Jonah...
而约拿浑身
bruised and beaten...
青一块紫一块
his ears like two seashells...
他的耳朵像两片贝壳一样……
still multitudinously murmuring
of the ocean...
还一直回响着大海的声音
Jonah did the Almighty's bidding.
约拿听从了全能者的吩咐
And what was that, shipmates?
那是什么，船友们？
To preach the truth
in the face of falsehood!
在谎言面前宣扬真理!
No, shipmates. Woe to him who seeks
to pour oil on the troubled waters...
不，船友们。那些想在浑水上浇油的有祸了，
when God has brewed them into a gale.
因为神已经把浑水化作狂风
Yea, woe to him who,
as the pilot Paul has it...
那像领航的保罗一样传道给人听的，
while preaching to others
is himself a castaway.
自己却被弃绝了的，有祸了
Delight is to him...
而那些
who, against the proud gods
and commodores of this earth...
凡与世上狂傲的神和同伴相争
stands forth his own inexorable self...
彰显自己刚强之心的，便为有福
who destroys all sin
though he pluck it out...
虽然他从元老院和法官的袍子底下把罪都拔出来
from under the robes
of senators and judges!
却把一切罪都消灭了的，便为有福
And eternal delight shall be his...
而来躺下的人，
who, coming to lay him down, can say:
他必永远喜乐，并说：
"O Father...
噢，天父
"mortal or immortal...
无论我是凡人还是神仙
"here I die.
我都会在这里死去
"l have striven to be thine...
我已经努力让自己属于你
"more than to be this world's...
胜过属于这个世界
"or mine own.
或是我自己
"Yet this is nothing.
然而这不算什么
"l leave eternity to thee.
我把永恒留给你
"For what is man...
人算什么
"that he should live out
the lifetime of his God?"
怎么能和神共生死呢？"
And 50.
第50页
Three time I count 50.
我用了三次数到了50页
Many pages, many.
太多页了，太多页
A big book.
一本大厚书
You know words?
你识字吗？
I know picture. This whale.
我认得这幅画，这条鲸鱼
You speak words.
你帮我读一下文字部分
"The heart of the whale is larger...
“鲸鱼的心脏
"than the pipe of the waterworks
at London Bridge.
比伦敦桥自来水厂的水管还要粗大
"The water in that pipe
is not so thick or fast...
水管里的水流的密度和速度
"as the blood pumping
from the heart of the whale."
还赶不上鲸鱼心脏里血液的循环
True. Thank you.
是真的，谢谢你
Queequeg...
魁魁格……
who are you? Where are you from?
你是谁，你从哪来？
My father king. I chief.
我父亲是国王，我是酋长
My uncle a high priest in islands...
我叔叔是遥远的西南方
west south far away.
岛屿上的大祭司
Ship come by island.
船只从岛屿旁经过
I take canoe, I sail, I swim...
我做了条独木舟划过去，然后再游泳
I climb rope, I hide.
顺着绳子爬上船，藏起来
Ship take me far. Many years.
船把我带到远方，很多年
See all world.
环游世界
Odd. Many is the Christian wishes
he was a dark man on a cannibal isle.
奇怪，很多基督徒都希望他是个深色皮肤的食人族
-What next, Queequeg?  下一步做什么，魁魁格？
-Sail ship. You? 出海，你呢？
Tomorrow I hope to sign aboard any ship
in search of whales.
明天我希望能随便上一搜捕鲸船
I sign, too. Your boat, my boat.
我也去，你上哪艘船，我就上那艘船
I eat same food. We sail on same waters.
我们同吃同住，一起航海
We kill same whale.
我们一起捕鲸
We friends.
我们是朋友
Same blood, same head, all same.
同样的血液，同样的头，都一样
Well, which will it be, Queequeg?
那，选哪一条船呢，魁魁格？
The Tit-bit? Not a bad ship.
珍品号，这艘船不赖
What do you say to the Devil-dam?
你觉得 恶魔大坝 怎么样？
Pequod.
裴廓德号
Well, now.
好，来吧
Look at the ivory she's wearing.
瞧她上面这些象牙啊
She's all tricked out
in the bones of her victims.
她周身都用战利品的骨头作为装饰
Those cleats made from whale's teeth.
那些楔子都是鲸鱼的牙做的
And the tiller, Queequeg,
it's carved from a whale's jaw.
还有这舵柄，魁魁格，是用鲸鱼的颚骨雕刻出来的
Ahoy there! Someone aboard?
喂，有人上船吗？
Is this the captain of the Pequod?
你是裴廓德号的船长吗？
What doest thee want of the captain?
你们想要见船长干什么？
We were thinking of shipping.
我们想要出海
Thee art thinking of shipping.
你们想要出海
I art.... I mean, I doest.
我是，我是说，我不是……
-Making sport of me, lad?  你在逗我玩吗，小伙子？
-No. I just fell into that manner of speech.  不，我只是不太会语法
If I weren't a Quaker and a man of peace...
如果我不是贵格会(属于基督教派，废除礼仪，反对暴力和战争)的教徒，而且爱好和平的话……
I'd fetch thee clout on the side of thy head,
my lad, just to make sure.
我要打你一个耳光，我的孩子，只是为了确定一下。
I see thee art no New Bedford man.
我看你们不是新贝德福德本地人啊
Doest know nothing at all about whaling,
I daresay.
我敢说你们对捕鲸一窍不通吧
I've had several voyages
in the merchant service.
我以前跟着商船出过几次海
Merchant service? Flukes, man.
商船？那只是侥幸，真的
-What takes thee whaling? 你们为什么要捕鲸？
-Sir, I want to see what whaling is like. 长官，我想看看鲸鱼是什么样
Have you seen Ahab,
the captain of this ship?
你们见过这艘船的船长亚哈了吗？
If you want to know what whaling is...
如果你们想知道捕鲸是怎么回事……
the n you'll know by clapping an eye
on Captain Ahab.
你们先看一眼亚哈船长就知道了
You'll see a man torn apart
from crown to heel...
你们可以看到一个被从头到脚撕碎
and spliced together with
sperm whalebone in place of what's missing.
然后再用抹香鲸的须子缝合起来的人
His looks tell more than any church-had
sermon about the mortality of man.
他的外表比任何教堂里关于人类死亡的说教都更能说明问题
And a whale did that?
这是一只鲸鱼干的？
A whale as big as an island.
一头像岛一样大的鲸鱼
Art thee the man to pitch a harpoon
down a whale's throat and jump after it?
你是那种能把鱼叉扎进鲸鱼的喉咙然后再跳上去的人吗？
I am, sir...
是的，长官……
if it should be positively indispensable
to do so.
如果这样做是必要的话
Come along, then.
那就过来吧
Bildad, stir yourself.
This young man says he wants to ship.
比勒达，打起精神来。 这个年轻人说他想出海
-Hast ever been a pirate, hast thee?  你没当过海盗吧？
-Never.从来有
-Didst not murder thy last captain at sea?  上次出海没有把船长杀掉吧？
-lndeed not. 真没有
He'll do.
他没问题了
-What pay shall we give him? 我们怎么给他开工资？
-The 777th part. 777先令
-Would not be too much? 这不会太多了吗？
-For this strapping lad? Not half enough.  这么魁梧的小伙子？ 一点都不多
Captain Peleg, thee hast a generous heart.
法勒船长，你有一颗慷慨的心。
But thee must consider the duty thee owest
to the other owners of this ship...
但是你必须考虑你对这艘船的其他船主所负的责任
widows and orphans, many of them.
他们很多是寡妇和孤儿，
If we too abundantly reward
the labors of this young man...
如果我们给这个年轻人过高的薪酬……
we'll be taking bread from their mouths.
我们会让他们吃不上饭的
I'm putting him down
for the 300th part of the profit.
从利润里出300先令给他
You hear, Bildad? The 300th part, I say.
你听见了，比勒达？ 我说300先令
"Lay not up for yourself
treasures upon earth...
“不要把自己的财报财富堆积在地上
"where moth and rust do corrupt."
蛀虫和铁锈会侵蚀它们……”
-My last pay was--   我上一次的工资是
-The 777th part seems fair enough to me.  我觉得777 先令挺公道的
-The 300th.就 300先令
-Don't thank me, lad. I only do thee justice. 别谢我，我只是秉公办事
What holds thee? Sign.
你还犹豫什么？ 签字
-Sir, it's Captain Ahab.  长官，关于亚哈船长
-What about him?  他怎么了？
Was not Ahab of old a very wicked king?
亚哈不是古代一个很邪恶的暴君吗？
And when he was slain,
did the dogs not lick his blood?
当他被杀的时候，连狗都不会舔他的血？
Look, lad,
Captain Ahab did not name himself.
听着，小伙子，亚哈船长的名字也不是他自己起的
Sign the paper now, and wrong him not
because he happens to have a wicked name.
现在就把这文件签了，不要因为他碰巧有一个邪恶的名字而误会他
Now for that son of darkness
that is thy friend.
现在是为你那个深色皮肤的朋友
Queequeg, step forward.
魁魁格，站出来
What say you, Bildad?
你说呢，比勒达？
I suspect thee art not a Christian.
我怀疑你不是个基督徒
Doest thee attend church on Sundays?
你礼拜天去教堂吗？
Doest thee know and obey
the Ten Commandments?
你们知道遵从十诫吗？
God, man.
上帝啊
Take the pen. Make thy mark.
Sign now for a 60th part of our profit.
拿笔，先做个记号, 签好了就可以领六十先令
Put there, quick.
这里，快点
Lantern kegs: 15.
灯笼桶： 15
Rubber pipes: 10.
橡皮管：10
Avast, there!
停!
Are you going aboard, shipmate?
你要去国外吗，船友？
Have you signed to sail on that ship?
你已经签约这艘船了？
Have you signed to sail the Pequod, I say?
我说，你们已经签约斐廓德号了吗？
Was there anything down
about signing away your souls?
你们对于出卖自己的灵魂有什么问题吗？
-What? 什么？
-Perhaps you haven't got any. 可能你根本就没有灵魂
-Have you met old Ahab yet?  你见过老亚哈了吗？
-What are you jabbering about? 你在支支吾吾些什么？
Did they say how his mother birthed him,
gave him his evil name, and died?
他们告没告诉你他的妈妈如何生下他，起了这个邪恶的名字，然后死去的？
How God's lightning struck down
and branded him?
上帝的闪电是如何击中他, 留下烙印的？
How he spat in the holy goblet
in church of Valparaiso?
他是如何在 瓦尔帕莱索（智利中部城市）的教堂里朝圣杯里吐痰的？
Did they tell you about his last voyage?
他们和你讲他上一次航行了吗？
I know all about him being crippled
by a whale. Come on.
我对他被一条鲸鱼弄残了腿这事很清楚。走吧
All about it? You're sure you do? Sure?
整件事情？你确认你很清楚，真的吗？
Did they say how the whale marked him
inside and out...
他们有没有说鲸鱼是如何把他从头到脚都做了标记……
and a mischief was worked on his soul?
No, I don't think they did.
而且让他的精神出了问题？
不，他们没说
-Who'd know? Not many, I guess. 谁知道呢？我想没几个人
-You can't fool us.  你骗不了我们
It's very easy for a man to look like
he's got a great secret.
一个人想要装作自己知道个大秘密是很容易的
I have, lad.
我真的知道，小伙子
At sea one day,
you'll smell land where there be no land.
在海上，总有一天你会在没有陆地的地方闻到陆地的气味
On that day, Ahab will go to his grave,
but he'll rise again within the hour.
到那日，亚哈必死，但很快会再次起身
He will rise and beckon.
他会起身然后招手
Then all, all save one, shall follow.
然后所有的人，除了一个之外，都将追随他的命运
Morning, shipmates. Morning.
早上好，船友们，早上好
May the heavens bless you.
愿上天保佑你们
Hey, you.
嘿，我说
-What's your name?  你叫什么名字？
-Elijah. 以利亚
My name is Elijah.
我叫以利亚
-Bible? 要圣经吗？
-No, thank you, Aunt Charity, I have mine. 不用了，谢谢嬷嬷，我自己有
Bible?
要圣经吗？
-Thank you, ma'am.  谢谢女士
-God bless you. 愿上帝保佑你
Don't whale it too much on the Lord's day.
But don't lose a fair chance, either.
在礼拜日上不要捕太多鲸鱼，但也不要错过一次公平的机会
Spring, you sons of bachelors!
Jump, spring, there, green pants!
快爬，你们这些小杂毛！跳上去，快爬，穿绿裤子的！
You, Scotchcap!
你，带无边帽的！
-Yes?  怎么了？
-Spring! 动起来！
Good white cedar plank is 3% more this year
than the last.
今年优质白雪松木板比去年贵了3%
Hoist the yards!
升起帆桁！
Our boots and clothes are all in pawn
我们典当了衣服和鞋子
Go down, you blood red roses, go down
下去吧，你这鲜红的玫瑰，下去吧
And it's mighty drafty
round the Cape of Storms
在风暴之角，周围风很大
Go down, you blood red roses, go down
下去吧，你这鲜红的玫瑰，下去吧
Oh, you pinks and posies
哦，你们这些粉红色的
Go down, you blood red roses, go down
下去吧，你这鲜红的玫瑰，下去吧
Take care of the butter.
20 cents a pound, it is.
看好黄油，20美分一磅呢！
Bildad, stop palavering away.
比勒达 ，别废话了
Three years is a long while going.
三年是很长的时间
God have you in his holy keeping.
上帝会照看好你们的
For that is where them whalefish blow
因为那是他们捕鲸的地方
Go down, you blood red roses
下去吧，你这鲜红的玫瑰，下去吧
Avast! Heave it!
停！举起来！
Heave it there!
扔到那边！
Heave away, forward.
起锚，前进
There 's some that's bound
for New York town
有一些是开往纽约的
And others is bound for France
还有一些开往法国
Heave away, my Johnny
起锚了，我的孩子
Heave away
起锚了
And some that's bound for the Bengal Bay
还有些开往孟加拉湾
To teach them whales to dance
教那里的鲸鱼跳舞
And away, my Johnny boy
起锚了，我的孩子
We're all bound to go
我们都要出发了
Come all you hard-weathered sailors
来吧，你们这些从风暴角来的
Who round the Cape of Storms
饱经风霜的水手
Heave away, my Johnny
起锚了，我的孩子
Heave away
起锚了
Be sure your boots and oilskins on
一定要穿好靴子和雨衣
Or you'll wish you'd never been born
不然你们会后悔的
And away, my Johnny boy
起锚了，我的孩子
We 're all bound to go
我们都要出发了
Set the topsails!
定好后帆！
Up helm.
使船向风
And around the world!
驶向世界！
The Pequod beat an easterly course
toward the whaling grounds off the Azores.
"裴廓德号"向东驶去
去亚速尔群岛附近的捕鲸场
The crew came from all the isles of the sea,
all the ends of the earth:
船员们来自五湖四海，全球各地：
from Greenland to Mombasa...
从格陵兰（世界上最大的岛屿)到蒙巴萨(肯尼亚第二大城市）…
from Clyde to Kokovoko.
从克莱德（位于西南苏格兰）到Kokovoko（魁魁格的家乡，实际不存在）
Flask, the third mate,
bullied everybody bigger than himself...
大副弗拉斯克，欺负每一个块头比较自己大的人…
particularly whales,
with whom he carried on a one-sided feud...
尤其对鲸鱼他有一种单方面的积怨……
as though the great leviathans
had mortally insulted him and his forebears.
就像大海兽对他和他的祖先进行了致命的侮辱一样。
And there was Pip, black little Pip,
the cabin boy from Alabama.
那是匹普，黑皮肤的小匹普，
来自阿拉巴马州的客舱服务员。
Second in command was Starbuck...
副船长是斯达巴克
whose Quaker stock had furnished
many a whaleboat with its champion.
他的贵格会血统，把很多拥护者带上了捕鲸小艇
No crusader after perils...
和那些追逐危险的十字军战士不同
his courage was one of the great staples
of the ship, like beef or flour:
他的勇气在需要的时候，是这艘船主要的支柱之一,
there when required,
and not to be foolishly wasted.
就如同牛肉或面粉一样: 不能被轻易浪费
Ship 's carpenter:
船上的木匠：
he fixed everything
from stove boats to broken arms and legs.
他修理从破船到断臂在内的一切
Perth, the blacksmith, lived amidst
thick, hovering flights of sparks.
铁匠柏斯,终日生活在盘旋在空中的浓密火星之中
He breathed them in and out.
They nested in his ears.
他把它们吸入又呼出，耳朵里也积攒了不少
But Perth cared not because, as he said...
不过柏斯不在乎，他说：
he was scorched all over,
and you cannot scorch a scar.
他浑身都被烫了一个遍，而疤痕是不怕烫的
Queequeg was our first harpooneer.
魁魁格是我们第一个鱼叉手
Next was Tashtego, the Indian
from a great warrior race of red men...
下一个是塔斯蒂哥，美洲印第安人，来自一个著名战斗种族…
come to hunt whale instead of buffalo.
放弃了野牛而来捕鲸
Then Daggoo, who got his boldness
and majesty and grace...
然后是达古，他独自杀死了一只狮子并把肉分给族人
from having killed a lion single-handed
and partaken of its flesh.
他因此赢得了勇气，威严和荣耀
Stubb, the second mate.
斯塔布，二副。
Stubb, who 'd have tied a bowline
in the devil's tail for a joke.
斯塔布，他为了好玩可以在魔鬼的尾巴上打个领结
Carefree, foolish, laughing, wise Stubb.
无忧无虑，总在傻笑的聪明的斯塔布
Of our supreme lord and dictator,
there was no sign.
至于我们的最高领袖和独裁者,没有任何动静。
Ahab stayed silent
behind his locked door...
整个白天,亚哈总是待在他紧锁的门后
all the daylight hours.
保持沉默……
It's him again. It's Ahab.
又是他，是亚哈
Ahab come out in moonlight.
亚哈在月亮升起时出来活动
Strange.
奇怪
Only at night.
只在晚上
Every night, all alone, walking the deck.
每天晚上，独自一人，在甲板上踱步
"Sand it, holystone it," they say.
"用砂纸打磨，再用磨石磨平” 他们说
And when you're done, what happens?
做完之后呢，会怎么样？
"Start over again," they say.
他们会说 ”再来一遍，“
"Clean it up, sand it down, buff it off."
"擦干净，磨平，再擦亮"
Keeps you busy, lad. No time for mischief.
Here we go.
总是忙个不停，没时间瞎折腾，我们开始干吧
Looming straight up and over us...
亚哈船长站在那里
Like a solid iron figurehead
suddenly thrust into our vision...
就像一个坚硬的铁头像突然闯入我们的视野……
stood Captain Ahab.
在我们的上方赫然耸现
His whole, high, broad form...
他那高大、宽阔的身躯……
weighed down upon a barbaric white leg
carved from the jawbone of a whale.
都压在一条用鲸的颚骨雕刻而成的野蛮的白腿上
He did not feel the wind
or smell the salt air.
他感觉不到海风或是闻一闻咸咸的空气。
He only stood staring at the horizon...
他只是站在那里盯着地平线……
with the marks of some inner crucifixion
and woe deep in his face.
带着内心苦难的痕迹,他脸上露出深深的悲哀。
-Mr. Starbuck. 斯达巴克先生
-Sir?  船长？
Call everybody aft.
把大家召集到船尾
All hands aft!
全体到船尾集合！
Down, mastheads!
桅顶上的，快下来！
What do you do
when you see a whale, men?
看到鲸鱼的时候你会怎么做，伙计们？
-Sing out for him! 唱起战歌！
-Aye! 对！
-Good. What do you do next? 好，接下来呢？
-Lower away, and after him!  放下小艇，追上去！
And what tune is it you pull to, men?
你们要唱什么歌，伙计们？
A dead whale or a stove boat!
不是鲸鱼死就是小艇沉！(流传于太平洋陆军的民歌，stove这里是busted的意思）
All you mastheaders...
桅顶上放哨的……
now hear me.
现在听我说
You're to look...
你们要找的是
for a white whale.
一只白色的白鲸
A whale as white and as big
as a mountain of snow.
一只像雪山一样巨大而洁白的鲸鱼
You see this Spanish gold ounce?
看到这枚西班牙金币了吗?
Carpenter, hand me your top maul.
木匠，把你的大锤递给我。
Whosoever of ye...
无论谁
finds me that white whale...
帮我找到那只白鲸
ye shall have this Spanish gold ounce,
my boys.
就可以得到这枚西班牙金币
It's a white whale, I say.
我说,那是一只白色的鲸鱼
Skin your eyes for him.
擦亮眼睛好好找
Captain, sir, could it be the one that fantails
a little curious before he go down?
船长先生, 那只鲸鱼下潜前会扬起奇特的尾鳍?
Has he a curious spout,
all bushy and mighty quick and high, sir?
他会喷出奇特的水柱, 又快又高 , 汹涌有力?
And irons in his hide, many irons,
all twist around?
他的后背上有很多铁器，全都被折弯了？
Aye, like corkscrews.
是的,就像开瓶器上的螺丝一样
He's struck full of harpoons, men.
他身上插满了鱼叉,伙计们
And his spout is a big one,
like a whole shock of wheat.
他喷出的水柱很粗大,像整整一捆小麦一样
And he fantails like a broken jib in a storm.
他的尾鳍在风暴中就像一节三角帆
Death, men, you've seen him.
死神，伙计们，你们见过他
It's Moby Dick.
就是莫比.迪克
Captain Ahab...
亚哈船长……
was it not Moby Dick took off thy leg?
不就是莫比.迪克让你丢了条腿吗？
Aye.
是的
It was Moby Dick...
正是莫比.迪克
that tore my soul and body
until they bled into each other.
撕碎了我的灵魂和肉体再把他们混在一起
I'll follow him around the Horn...
我会跟着他到好望角
and around the Norway Maelstrom...
到挪威旋涡……
and around perdition's flames...
到地狱的火焰中……
before I give him up.
也不会放弃
This is what you've shipped for, men.
伙计们，你们出海的目的
To chase that white whale
on both sides of land...
就是要追捕这条白鲸
and over all sides of earth...
走遍天涯海角
until he spouts black blood
and rolls dead out.
直到他喷出黑色的血液，翻滚着死去
What say ye?
你说什么
I think you do look brave.
我觉得你们看着很勇敢
-Will you splice hands on it? 你们能在这件事上联手吗？
-Aye! 是的！
Steward,
go draw the great measure of grog.
管家,去拿一大罐格罗格酒(掺热水的朗姆烈酒)。
Harpooneers, get your weapons.
Mates, your lances.
鱼叉手们，拿好武器。
朋友们, 你的长矛。
Ye mariners, now ring me in...
水手们，现在围到我身边来
that I may revive a noble custom
of my fisherman fathers.
这样我可以重现一种我渔民父辈们的高贵风俗
The measure. Drink and pass.
这壶酒，喝一口然后传给下一位
Round with it, round.
把酒传一圈，传起来
Quick draughts, long swallows, men.
快速喝一口，吞下肚，伙计们
It's hot as Satan's hoof.
像撒旦的蹄子一样灼热
That way it went, this way it comes.
从那边过去，从这边过来
It spiralizes in ye.
赐予汝等神圣的力量
Here, hand it me.
来，给我
Well done. Almost drained.
很好，几乎喝干了
Advance, mates.
前进，朋友
Cross your lances.
把你们的长矛交叉
Now, let me touch the axis.
让我摸摸轴心的部分
Do you feel it?
你能感觉到吗？
That same lightning which struck me...
击中我的闪电
I now strike to this iron.
现在击中了这个铁器
Does it burn, men?
很烫吧，伙计们？
Harpooneers, break your weapons.
鱼叉手们，拆开你们的武器
Turn up the sockets.
把凹槽翻上来
Drink here, harpooneers...
喝吧，鱼叉手们……
drink and swear.
对酒发誓
God hunt us all...
如果我们不能把莫比迪克捉住杀死
if we do not hunt Moby Dick to his death.
上帝会把我们一网打尽
Death to Moby Dick!
为了莫比迪克之死!
Moby Dick.
莫比迪克
Do they name certain whales, then?
他们给鲸鱼起名字吗？
Aye. Special, people-murdering whales
with long histories.
是的，那些有悠久历史的特别的杀人鲸
Whales that have killed 10 times 100 men.
那些杀了上千人的鲸鱼
Whales like Timor Tim,
New Zealand Tom...
像是帝汶岛的蒂姆，新西兰的汤姆，
or Morquan, King of the Japan Seas.
或者摩根，日本海的王者
Whales have big names
to go with big doings.
干过大事的鲸鱼都会扬名立万
The biggest of them all is Moby Dick.
其中名气最大的就是莫比迪克
A white whale, Ahab said.
亚哈说是一头白鲸
Can a whale be white?
鲸鱼有白色的吗？
He's white,
whiter than all the snow that ever fell.
他是白色的，比你见过的所有雪都要白
Like a great marble tombstone,
he is, afloat.
像是一座漂在海面的大理石的墓碑
Wherever he swims,
white sky birds wheel above him.
凡是他游过的地方，白色的鸟在上空盘旋
-Birds white as the angels.  像天使一样洁白的鸟
-Which oceans does he swim in, Manxman? 他在哪里出没，马恩岛人？
All oceans. He's been spied
in different seas 1,000 mile apart...
所有的海域，在相距一千英里之外的不同地方
-on the same day at the same hour. 在同一时间都见过他的踪迹
-Maybe it just ain't one whale...  也许他不是一头白鲸……
but a whole breed. 而是一群
Maybe Moby Dick's 100 whales. 莫比迪克可能是一百只鲸鱼组成的鱼群
Then they all have crooked jaws
and wrinkled brows...
他们都有歪斜的颚骨和皱褶的额头……
and a dozen irons stuck
in their white humps.
白色的驼峰上插着十几把鱼叉
Aye, many have lowered for Moby Dick
and struck him...
是的，很多人都下艇叉过莫比迪克
only to know his vengeance.
却只是领教到他的报复
Some have boasted they killed him...
有人吹嘘他们杀了他
but always he comes gliding back...
可他总是轻松的回归……
huge and white and secret-like.
巨大的白色的，谜一样的存在
Immortal, he is, they say.
他们说，他是不死之身
You ain't trying to scare us, Manxman?
你不是在吓唬我们吧，马恩岛人？
I say what I say.
我说的就是这些
There she blows!
发现鲸鱼！
Sperm whale to starboard!
There she blows!
抹香鲸在右舷! 正在喷水！
There go flukes!
尾叶在那里！
-Flukes gone down! 尾叶潜下去了！
-Larboard!  左舷！
Stow all line tubs!
装载所有小艇（里面有捕鲸用的绳子）!
Fill up the mainsail!
主帆加满！
Bear away, boats!
上小艇，去抢头功吧！
-Bet you a dollar we strike first!  赌一美元我们先抓到！
-Right, Stubb. A dollar you don't.  好的，斯塔布，你输了一美元
That's it, boys.
就这样，孩子们
Pull, my men.
划啊，我的伙计们
Why in the name of gudgeons
and ginger cakes...
你们是都没吃饱吗
can't ye pull and start your eyes out?
你们就不能睁大眼睛划船吗？
Why don't you break your backbones, boys? 使出吃奶的劲儿来，孩子们？
Pull, then. 用力划
Do pull, will you, please? So, so now.
用力划啊，使劲儿行吗? 像现在这样
Pull, boys! Pull!
划啊，孩子们，划啊！
Pull, blast you!
划啊，被你们气死了！
Take the oars off!
把桨拿下来划!
Pull, my good boys.
划啊，我的好孩子
That's fine.
好的
Pull.
划啊
Pull, my good boys.
用力划，好孩子
Long and strong, boys.
每下都用力划到底，孩子们
Pull and burst all your livers and lungs!
肝和肺都炸裂也没关系，用力划！
Stop snoring, you sleepers!
别打呼噜了，你们这些瞌睡虫！
Pull, can't ye? Pull!
划啊，你们行不行啊，用力！
Merrily, hearts!
高兴点，用点心！
Fine.
好的
That's fine.
很好
Come on, men. Pull ahead.
来吧，伙计们，向前划
Pull, can't ye?
用力划，行吗？
Man overboard!
有人落水！
Cut him loose.
切断绳子
Queequeg, my fine friend,
does this sort of thing happen very often?
魁魁格，我的好朋友，这种事经常发生吗？
True, true.
是的，是的
Heave away, boys!
起锚，孩子们
And so we stripped our first whale...
于是我们把捕到的第一只鲸鱼剥了皮
and boiled the blubber down
to a fine, pure oil...
用鲸脂熬成的上好的鲸鱼油
that would keep the lamps burning
in a thousand homes...
可以让上千个家庭点亮油灯
the clocks ticking on their mantelpieces...
让他们壁炉上的时钟滴答作响……
and perhaps anoint the head of a king.
可能还能抹上国王的头
And when at last we cast
the whale 's bared bones into the sea...
当最后我们把鲸鱼的裸露的骨头投进大海时…
we were in no way sad at its funeral.
我们在它的葬礼上毫不悲伤
Captain.
船长
-Starbuck?  斯达巴克？
-Aye, Captain. 是，船长
It's late. You should turn in.
很晚了，你该上床睡觉了
Sleep?
睡觉？
That bed is a coffin...
那床就像一口棺材……
and those are winding sheets.
那些就是裹尸布
I do not sleep. I die.
我不睡觉，我会死的
The prize furnished 85 barrels of oil, sir.
They're all capped and stored.
一共炼出来85桶油，长官
都盖上盖子并存储起来了
-How is the wind? 风向怎么样?
-North, northeast and steady. 北风,东北风很稳定
Make the most of it. I do not wish
to linger on this Cape Verde ground.
充分利用它,我不希望 徘徊在佛得角的土地上。
We're bound for the Pacific,
Mr. Starbuck, straightaway.
我们要去太平洋 斯达巴克先生,一直向前
You will plot a course
south by east to the line...
你会绘制出一条准确的南偏东的航线……
and so southeast
to pick up the Guinea current.
精确的东南向，可以遇到几内亚洋流
Aye, aye, sir.
是的,是的,长官
Mr. Starbuck...
斯达巴克先生
did you ever ponder the movements
of whales around the four oceans?
你有没有仔细琢磨过些四大洋附近鲸鱼的运动规律?
I only know that they appear at
certain feeding grounds in certain seasons.
我只知道他们在特定的季节出现在特定的觅食地。
Look here.
看这里
Logbooks from the time
New Bedford men first went a-whaling...
新贝德福德人刚开始从事捕鲸时候的日志……
helped me draw this chart.
帮我画出了这张海图
It divides the oceans into areas of
five degrees of latitude by five of longitude.
它把海洋按纬度和纬度分成了 5x5的区域
Here are the months of the years,
the ships that passed...
这里是年月,经过的船只
how long they lingered,
the whales they saw:
他们逗留了多久，他们看到的鲸鱼:
what size, what color,
how many, where heading.
什么尺寸，什么颜色，
数量多少，往哪里游
-I never saw the like. 我从来没见过这样的
-This way, the humpbacks go... 座头鲸往这边
the blue, the right...
蓝鲸,去右边
the spermaceti.
鲸脑油
Sea mile by sea mile.
一海里一海里的
I know their hidden journeys
as I know the veins in my arm.
我知道他们的秘密航线, 就像我对手臂上静脉的了解一样。
You mean to say that
their journeys can be foretold?
你的意思是说他们的轨迹可以预知吗?
Aye, like the blood pumping in my veins
from heart to hand.
是啊，就像我静脉里的血液一样
从心脏到手掌。
If this be so, we can follow along
with the herds, killing as we go...
如果是这样，我们可以跟着他们的鱼群，一边捕猎…
and fill our hold in record time.
在创纪录的时间里完成我们的任务
So we shall, Mr. Starbuck. So we shall...
我们可以, 斯达巴克先生, 我们可以
once we've attended to
our bigger business.
一旦我们开始更大的生意。
What is that business, Captain?
那是什么，船长?
Him, Mr. Starbuck. Him.
他, 斯达巴克先生, 他
What's true of the herds holds largely
for the great solitaries and hermits.
鲸鱼群的规律,很大程度上也适用于那些独居的隐士
If these sources tell the truth,
and my calculations are not faulty...
如果这些信息是真的, 而我的计算没有出错的话…
he now swims the waters off Good Hope...
他现在游出了好望角……
and all the Indian Ocean lies before him.
整个印度洋都在他面前
Next month, he cruises the Bengal Bay,
March, the Sulu Sea...
下个月，他将巡游孟加拉湾，
三月，苏禄海……
running eastward
to the gateway of the Pacific.
向东游去,到太平洋的门户
I shall be waiting for him...
我会在四月的新月
here...
在这里
at new moon in April.
等着他
Mr. Starbuck.
斯达巴克先生
-I must give the helmsman our course. 我必须给舵手指明方向
-Come about, sir. 回来，先生
Why are you wearing that long face? 你为什么一副不乐意的样子?
Are you not game for Moby Dick? 你不想抓到莫比迪克吗?
Captain Ahab,
I am game for any kind of death...
亚哈船长,
我愿意接受任何形式的死亡
if it comes in the way
of the business we follow. That be known.
如果它阻碍到我们所从事的事业,这你应该知道
But I came here to hunt whales,
not my commander's vengeance.
但我来这里是为了捕鲸,不是为我的指挥官复仇。
How many barrels of sperm oil
will thy vengeance yield?
为你报仇又能生产出多少桶鲸油呢?
What will it fetch
on the New Bedford market?
在新贝德福德市场上它能卖多少钱?
Money is not the measurer, man.
钱不是衡量的标准，伙计。
It will fetch me a great premium...
它会给我心里
here.
带来很大的安慰
To be enraged with a dumb brute
that acted out of blind instinct...
被一个基于本能盲目行事的哑巴畜生所激怒
is blasphemous.
这是一种亵渎
Speak not to me of blasphemy, man.
别跟我说什么“亵渎”，伙计。
I'd strike the sun if it insulted me.
就算是太阳侮辱了我，我也会把它射下来
Look ye, Starbuck...
看看你，斯达巴克
all visible objects
are but as pasteboard masks.
所有看得见的物体都不过是纸板做的面具。
Some inscrutable yet reasoning thing...
某种神秘而又理性的东西……
puts forth the molding of their features.
构成了他们各自的特点
The white whale tasks me.
白鲸是我的任务
He heaps me.
他填满了我
Yet he is but a mask.
然而他也只是个面具
It is the thing behind the mask
I chiefly hate.
我主要是不喜欢面具后面的东西
The malignant thing
that has plagued and frightened man...
这恶毒的家伙从有时间开始
since time began.
就一直困扰和惊吓着人类
The thing that mauls
and mutilates our race...
这东西撕咬并残害我们的种族…
not killing us outright,
but letting us live on...
不是直接杀死我们,而是让我们活下去…
with half a heart and half a lung.
只剩下一半的心肺
God keep us, keep us all.
上帝保佑我们，保佑我们所有人。
The crew stands with me, Mr. Starbuck.
全体船员站在我这边，斯达巴克先生。
You heard them swear.
你听到他们宣誓了
Now...
现在
what say ye?
你还有什么要说吗？
Surely the best lance
out of all New Bedford...
毫无疑问，新贝德福德最好的长矛
will not hold back
from the greatest hunt of all?
也不会阻止最伟大的狩猎吧？
I say calmly back to thee, sir,
I am against thee.
我平静地回答你，长官，
我反对你。
Nut thee needn't fear Starbuck.
但是你不必害怕斯达巴克
Let Ahab beware Ahab.
让亚哈当心他自己
Beware thyself, my captain.
小心点，我的船长。
We left the winter seas behind...
我们已经把冬天的海洋抛在身后
and sailed under the hot sun south.
在烈日下向南航行
South, past the unseen sprawl of Africa...
向南，越过看不见的非洲大陆……
until we rounded the Cape of Storms and
steered a bold course east and northeast...
直到我们绕过风暴角
大胆地向东和东北航行
for the Indian Ocean and beyond.
去到印度洋更远的地方。
-You there, lad, go aloft. 你，小伙子，到上面去
-Aye, aye, sir. 是的，长官
And so I served my first watch
in the masthead...
于是，在一种优美流畅的节奏之中
held in a great, gliding rhythm.
我第一次爬到桅顶上放哨……
No life in me except that life imparted...
我的体内仅有的生命力
by a gently rolling ship...
远离所有陆地居民的照料
remote from all the cares
of the people of the land.
都是那艘轻轻摇晃的船所给予的。
There she blows!
鲸鱼喷水！
Where away? How many?
在哪里？ 有几只？
Starboard bow, Mr. Stubb!
右舷，斯塔布先生!
-Two! No, four of them! 两只，不，是四只！
-What's that boy yelling?  那孩子在喊什么？
Six, seven of them!
六只，七只！
There's three dozen more of them!
有三四十只！
Look, Mr. Stubb! 100!
看，斯塔布先生，100只！
Come down from there!
The sun has baked your brains!
冷静点!
太阳把你的脑子烤焦了!
In the name of God, Mr. Stubb!
看在上帝的份上，斯塔布先生!
A hundred, two hundred whales!
一百，二百只鲸鱼!
Blast me dead, Mr. Flask.
该死的，弗拉斯克先生。
All hands, prepare to lower!
全体人员，准备放下小艇!
Another 40 barrels, sir.
又是40桶鲸鱼油，长官
Ahoy, there!
Captain Boomer knocking at your door.
喂, 有人吗
布玛船长在敲你的门。
-May he come in, sir? 他能进来吗，长官？
-Come aboard. 进来吧
Captain Boomer's my name, sir.
我是布玛船长，长官。
Ship's Samuel Enderby of London.
Eighteen months at sea.
在伦敦的塞缪尔·恩德比号轮船上服役，出海十八个月了。
-Ahab. 亚哈
-Captain Ahab, will you look out there? 亚哈船长，你能看看那里吗？
What a circus.
Did ever you see such a run?
真滑稽，你见过那样划船的吗?
Do it, boys! Do it!
加油，孩子们，加油！
Kill three for Captain Ahab
and three for me!
为亚哈船长杀三只
为我杀三只!
Never fear. I'll not scuttle your ship.
不要害怕。我不会弄沉你的船。
She's a beauty, eh, Captain?
Better than flesh and blood.
她很漂亮，对吗，上尉?
比血肉之躯更好
Like her so much
I've a mind to have me other arm cut off.
我太喜欢她了，恨不得把另外一条胳膊也砍了
The very thing for driving marlinspikes...
最适合用来钉马林钉（带尖的金属钉，用来固定成捆的绳子）
knocking sense
into green seamen's heads...
可以让刚出海的水手脑袋开窍……
and particularly good
for tapping kegs of rum...
而且敲朗姆酒桶也特别 好使……
if you get my meaning, Captain.
如果你明白我的意思，船长。
Pip, fetch rum.
皮普,上朗姆酒。
I see you're wearing
a bit of ivory yourself, sir.
我看你也装了象牙的假肢，先生
Lubbers with four limbs
don't know what they're missing.
四肢健全的人不知道他们错过了什么。
When I got this ivory jib,
all spanking new and scientific...
当我装上这副象牙假肢，全新的科学产物……
why, I could've thanked that whale.
我真该感谢那条鲸鱼。
Aye, a whale took me arm for his breakfast.
Devilish big, he was.
是啊，一条鲸鱼把我的胳膊当作它的早餐。
他真是太巨大了。
Pushed a tidal wave ahead with his nose...
用鼻子在身前掀起滔天巨浪……
and typhoons jumped off his flukes
when they banged the water.
当他们哗啦哗啦地打水的时候，尾叶能掀起台风
Old, he was,
and scarred like Jerusalem's hills.
他是老了,像耶路撒冷的山丘一样伤痕累累。
Captain Boomer, what was his color?
布玛上尉，他是什么颜色的?
He was white, sir. Think me crazy,
it's a fact. He was snowy white.
他是白色的，先生，你以为我疯了吧
可他确实是雪白的。
Had another chance at him a month ago.
一个月前又有一次机会碰到他。
You didn't kill him?
你没杀了他？
Bless you, no. Went his merry way.
"Good riddance," said l, and meant it.
谢天谢地, 没有， 他哪儿来的回哪儿去了
“总算走了，” 我这么说的时候是认真的。
Where did you last see the white whale?
你最后一次看到白鲸是在哪里?
Off the Cape of Good Hope.
离开好望角的时候
He was heading northeast
towards Madagascar.
他正朝东北方向的马达加斯加游去
Do you hear?
你听见了吗？
A white whale last month off Good Hope.
上个月一条白鲸离开了好望角。
My chart is right and true!
我的海图是对的，没错!
He'll be off Bikini
when the April moon is new.
在四月的新月，他会经过比基尼岛
Stop the hunt!
Pick up our boats. We're setting sail.
停止捕猎!
收起我们的小艇。我们起航。
But, Captain, those fine, big whales.
可是，船长，那么多上好的鲸鱼。
You men up there, get aloft!
你们这些人上去，上去!
I'll not sail with you, sir!
Bring my boat alongside.
我不和你一起航行，先生!
把我的小艇靠到边上来。
Mr. Starbuck, cut loose that carcass.
斯达巴克先生，把那个鲸鱼尸体割下来。
Pip, signal the men to return to ship.
皮普，给那些人发信号回船上来。
What ails ye, sir? Are ye stove-in drunk?
你怎么啦，先生?你喝醉了吗?
Captain Ahab, think what you're doing.
I beg thee, think.
亚哈船长，想想你在做什么。
我求求你，再考虑一下。
-Set the mainsail! 升起主帆！
-No, sir, no! 不，先生，不要！
Mr. Starbuck, are you opposing me?
斯达巴克先生，你是在反对我吗?
If so, I'll have you know
there is one God that is lord over the earth...
如果是的话，我会让你知道
世上只有一位神，主管整个世界。
and one captain over the Pequod.
斐廓德号也只有一位船长
Away now! Cut loose!
现在离开，走了 ！
Flask, what do you make of that?
弗拉斯克，你觉得那是什么意思？
Return to ship.
让我们回船上去
They're crazy, or I'm going blind.
他们疯了，不然就是我瞎了。
You're not blind. Something's up.
你没瞎，肯定有情况
Ye idiot, that's my whale
you're cutting loose!
白痴，那是我的鲸鱼
你让他跑了！
Come aboard. We're setting sail.
回船上来。我们要起航了。
Mr. Stubb, Mr. Flask, Did you not see
the pennant or hear my command?
斯塔布先生，弗拉斯克先生，你们没有看见信号旗或是听到我的命令吗?
Yes, sir, we did.
长官，我们看到了
Then why don't you obey?
那你们为什么不服从呢?
We will, sir, as soon as it sinks in.
Sort of bowled us over, Captain.
我们一旦明白过来，就立刻服从了。
只是有点出乎意料，长官
Weather's good, ship ain't sinking!
No one's lost overboard!
天气很好，船不会沉的!
没有一个人落水！
Got a fine harvest here.
Don't see no reason to leave.
我们大获丰收，搞不懂为什么要离开
I do not give reasons, Mr. Stubb.
I give orders.
我不做解释，斯塔布先生。
我只下命令。
Now, Captain, we're good men.
Our blood's up, that's all.
听着，船长，我们是好人。
我们热血沸腾，就这样。
We've been killing!
我们在宰鲸鱼！
A hard thing to stop killing
when you've been killing steady, sir.
你杀得性起的时候很难停下来，长官
We've been killing so fast,
our blood's so high...
我们杀得性起，热血沸腾……
we wouldn't have heard the last trump.
没听到到最后的号角。
Then hear me now:
那现在听我的：
Come aboard.
上船
All right, my hearties. Wake up!
Bestir yourselves.
好了，我的朋友们。醒醒吧!
犒劳一下自己
This is an evil voyage, I tell you.
我告诉你，这是一次邪恶的航行
If Ahab has his way...
如果按亚哈的命令行事……
thee, nor me, nor any member
of this ship's company...
你也好，我也好，任何这艘船的成员…
will ever see home again.
都再也回不了家了
Come now, Mr. Starbuck.
You're just plain gloomy.
得了，斯达巴克先生。
你只是太悲观了。
Moby Dick may be big,
but he ain't that big.
莫比迪克可能很大，
但他没那么大。
I do not fear Moby Dick.
我不怕莫比迪克
I fear the wrath of God.
我怕上帝发怒。
The wrath of God?
上帝发怒？
It is our task in life to kill whales...
我们这辈子的任务就是捕鲸
and furnish up their oil
for the lamps of the world.
来为世界上的灯提供灯油
If we perform that task well
and faithfully...
如果我们能忠实地完成好这项任务……
we do a service to mankind
that pleases Almighty God.
我们为人类做出的服务，会令全能的上帝喜悦的。
Aye.
是的
Ahab would deny all that.
亚哈否认这一切
He has taken us from the rich harvest
we were reaping...
他已经把我们从丰收的收割中带走
to satisfy his lust for vengeance.
去满足他复仇的私欲
He is twisting that which is holy...
他把本应神圣的使命
into something dark and purposeless.
变得黑暗而没有意义
He is a champion of darkness.
他是黑暗的拥护者
Ahab's red flag challenges the heavens.
亚哈的红旗向上帝发出挑战
Now, sir, if it's like that,
I don't wonder at you, a religious man...
现在，长官，如果是这样的话，
我能理解你，作为一个虔诚的人…
being a mite downcast.
有点沮丧
On the other hand,
don't much see what you can do about it.
另一方面，看不出你能做些什么。
Listen to this.
听着
"A captain who, from private motives...
“当一名船长出于私人动机……
"employs his vessel to another purpose
than that intended by the owners...
“把他的船用于船东计划之外的其他目的…
"is answerable to the charge
of usurpation...
是要被指控为“篡权”，并为此负责的
"and his crew is morally
and legally entitled...
而他的船员们出于道义和法律
"to employ forceful means
in wresting his command from him."
可以用强有力的手段从他手中夺取指挥权“
That's a mouthful. I swear.
这真拗口，我说
"Wrest his command from him "?
"夺去他的指挥权“？
-Does that mean take over? 这是 接管的意思吗？
-lt does, Mr. Flask. 是的，弗拉斯克先生
You ain't proposing we do any such thing?
你不会建议我们真这么干吧？
You're in dangerous waters, Mr. Starbuck.
Helm hard over. Come about.
你正处在危险的水域，斯达巴克先生
强行夺权，改变航向
Do thee not see...
你们看不出来……
that by serving Ahab
we share in his blasphemy?
服从亚哈的话，我们就是和他一样亵渎上帝吗?
Will thee risk that...
你们是宁愿冒这种风险
or stand with me and invoke the law?
还是和我一起求助于法律吗？
Pardon me, sir, this is my watch.
对不起，先生，到我站岗的时候了。
Captains can't break the law.
They is the law, as far as I'm concerned.
船长不会犯法的。
就我而言，他们就是法律。
Aye, and Ahab's a real fine captain, too.
是啊，而且亚哈也真是个好船长。
Why, there ain't a man aboard,
except you maybe...
不然为什么，船上的人除了你
wouldn't rather be kicked by him
than be knighted by the Queen of England.
都宁愿被他使唤，而不是被女王授勋
I'm done, then.
那我没话说了
Go write thy last will and testament.
去写你最后的遗嘱吧。
Aye, and do it laughing, sir.
是啊，我会边笑边写的，长官。
A laugh's the best answer
to all that's strange in life.
笑是对生活中所有的荒谬最好的回答
As we steered out toward Bikini...
当我们驶向比基尼岛的时候……
Ahab kept to his cabin
and was rarely seen.
亚哈一直待在他的船舱里，很少有人看见他。
The mastheads were empty
against the sky.
桅顶在天空的衬托下空无一人
No cry of "There she blows! "
was to entice us...
不再有人喊“鲸鱼喷水！"来让我们
from his single purpose.
在他唯一的目的之外，得到一些额外的动力
So, in April, with a new moon...
于是，在四月，伴随着新月……
we entered those waters...
我们进入了
where Ahab hoped to find the white whale.
亚哈希望找到白鲸的水域
Lookouts, bestir yourselves!
哨兵们，打起精神来
Lookouts up!
爬上岗哨！
Look alive, lads!
注意，小伙子们！
That gold belongs
to him with the sharpest eye.
金币是属于眼睛最尖的人的
That coin's worth $16.
I'll be first to sight the white whale.
那枚硬币值16美元。
我将是第一个发现白鲸的人。
Rum for me if I win the coin,
enough to dive into and never reach bottom.
如果我赢了这枚金币，给我买很多的朗姆酒
跳进酒桶的里，永远够不到底。
Man overboard!
有人落水！
Off the main yard.
从主甲板掉下去的
Sea boat's crew away.
救生艇成员就位
Not a sign of him.
没有他的踪迹
Yeah. Sea just swallowed him up.
是的。大海把他吞没了。
Queer.
奇怪
April 19, 1842.
1842年4月19日
Ahab's chart shows Moby Dick
and the new moon rising together.
亚哈的海图显示莫比迪克会和和新月一起出现
Nut the moon's lost his horns...
但是直到月亏开始
and there ain't no sign
of the white whale yet.
还是没有白鲸的踪迹
Seven days and seven nights on watch.
值了七天七夜的班
He ain't gone below, eats on deck,
sleeps standing up.
他不肯下去，在甲板上吃饭，站着睡觉。
How much longer can he hold?
他还能撑多久？
Nothing moves.
一点都不动
Nothing.
一动不动
Since the lookout fell into the sea...
自从岗哨落海之后
the wind don't move, the tide don't move.
没有一点风，也没有一点浪
Nothing.
一点都没有
Even the sun's nailed to the sky...
连太阳都钉在了天空上
Like that gold doubloon's
nailed to the mast.
就像钉在桅杆上的达布隆（古西班牙金币）。
You, lad, pull that gold coin off the mast.
你，小伙子，把那枚金币从桅杆上拿下来。
Throw it over the side.
Pay the sea a ransom.
把它扔到一边。向大海付一笔赎金。
Maybe it'll come back to life
and bring us a wind.
也许它会恢复生机，给我们带来一丝风。
Manxman, stop.
马恩岛人, 住手。
A cool wind.
一阵凉风
You, Manxman, stop!
你,马恩岛人, 住手!
Queequeg, what are you doing?
魁魁格，你在做什么？
See tomorrow here. Bones tell everything.
为明天占卜，骨头会告诉我一切。
Queequeg, what's the matter?
魁魁格，怎么了？
What do you see?
你看到什么了？
Get carpenter.
叫木匠来
What do you want the carpenter for?
你想叫木匠做什么？
Carpenter.
木匠
Here.
过来
-What can I do for you?  要我做什么？
-How much you build coffin for? 你做一口棺材要多少钱？
Coffin?
棺材？
$2 would do nicely.
2美元可以做的很好了
-Hold on.   等一下
-Build coffin. 6 feet, 7 inch. 做一口6英尺7英寸的棺材
Clean wood.
干净的木头
Make like best boat. Caulk and tar seams.
像做最好的船一样，接缝处用焦油做防渗水处理
No water come in.
让水进不来
Carve chief's feather on lid.
把酋长的羽毛刻在盖子上。
-6 feet 7 inches, it'll be. 6英尺7英寸，好的
-Queequeg, what's all this about? 魁魁格，这些是为了什么？
Money yours. Sea chest yours.
钱给你，储物箱给你
My harpoon yours.
我的鱼叉给你
Goodbye.
再见
What?
什么？
Queequeg, what are you talking about?
魁魁格，你在说什么啊？
Queequeg, listen to me!
魁魁格，听我说！
Say something.
说话啊
-What are we going to do?  我们现在怎么办？
-There's only one thing to do:  只有一件事可做：
build him his coffin.
帮他做棺材
You've got to eat.
你得吃点东西
A drink of water, then.
那就喝点水
Queequeg, if you go on like this,
I shall be very angry.
魁魁格，你再这样我要生气了
Queequeg, I absolutely forbid you to die.
魁魁格，我绝不让你死
Such behavior simply isn't Christian.
这种行为是违反基督教义的
In fact, it's downright pagan
and heathenish.
事实上，这完全是异教
Remember our oath?
记得我们的誓言吗
You promised to go where I go,
eat what I eat...
你答应过和我同吃同行
ship on my ship.
同船出海
I hold you to your promise, Queequeg.
我要你信守诺言，魁魁格
I've seen this before, lad.
我以前见过这种情况，小伙子
One day, for no reason,
they know that death is near.
有一天，他们无缘无故地知道死亡就在眼前。
They give away all their belongings
and say goodbye.
他们把所有的东西都送人，然后说再见。
Then they sit down to wait...
他们坐下来等待
and they just die.
死亡的到来
Mr. Starbuck, sir, Captain wants you.
斯达巴克先生，船长找你。
Sir?
船长
Mr. Starbuck, new orders.
斯达巴克先生，新的命令来了
We remain here until eight bells tonight...
我们在这里一直呆到今晚八点…
at which time we'll lower whaleboats...
那时我们就可以放下捕鲸小艇……
kedge the ship north...
收拢锚链，让船往北移动……
and row out of these waters.
从这片水域划出去。
Aye, aye, sir. At eight bells.
是的，是的，长官。八点钟。
I'm beating a march to you, Queequeg.
Get along.
魁魁格，我正在向你进军呢。跟上去
Get along quiet now, Queequeg.
安静的走吧，魁魁格
You follow the tide. It knows where to go.
你跟着海潮。它知道去哪里。
You get along with it.
It'll take you, Queequeg. Get along.
你跟上它，他会带领你，魁魁格，跟上去
Rig-a-dig.
忍一忍
He won't listen.
他不肯听
Queequeg's going away.
Know where he's going?
魁魁格要走了。知道他要去哪里吗?
Way, way up to Kokovoko.
一直到Kokovoko。
Back to Kokovoko, where he came from.
回到kokovoko，他来自那里
Queequeg, don't.
魁魁格，不要
-There she blows! 鲸鱼喷水！
-Queequeg, listen to me. Don't. 魁魁格，听我说，不要
Off the starboard beam!
在右舷横梁附近！
It's him.
是他
I know it's him.
我知道是他
Is it real?
真的？
Do you see it, too?
你也看见了？
Aye, we all see it.
是的，我们都看见了
But that don't mean it's real, necessarily.
但这并不意味着它一定是真实的。
Clear away the boats.
把小艇收拾干净。
Lower for him now, sir? At night?
现在就放小艇追他吗，长官? 在晚上?
Lower away.
放下小艇
Away boat's crews.
全体船员准备
He's sounded.
他听见了
Ship oars.
收桨
He's near.
他就在附近
He's very near.
他 很近了
Be ready for him.
准备迎击
He breaches!
他冲出来了！
The birds, they go.
海鸟飞走了
God, I'll lose him.
上帝啊，他要甩掉我了
Without a wind, we'll lose him!
没有风的话，我们跟不上他！
That ain't no whale.
That a great white god.
那不是鲸鱼。
那是一个白色的神。
About! Back to the ship!
可以了！回船上去！
We'll tie on and row for a wind.
我们要系上绳子，划桨等到起风
Long days and nights
we strained at the oars...
漫长的日日夜夜
我们使劲划桨……
while the white whale swam freely on...
白鲸自由地游着……
widening the waters between himself
and Ahab 's vengeance.
拉大着他与亚哈的仇恨之间的距离
A cloud on the starboard beam.
右舷横梁方向有朵云
Steer for the cloud, men. Bring her around.
驶向云朵，伙计们，转向
For the cloud! Starboard!
驶向云朵，右舷！
Pull quick!
快划！
Pull us into it, boys. Quick.
我们要到云里面去，孩子们。快。
Pull!
划啊！
That's it!
就是这样！
You raised the white whale first.
你第一个发现白鲸的
The gold doubloon is yours.
金币是你的了
Go on. Take it, sailor.
继续。拿走它,水手。
Wait now. Listen.
现在等一下，听我是
This man has his Spanish gold ounce.
这个人拿到了他的西班牙黄金盎司。
You shall have yours.
当莫比迪克被击中并被杀死时……
When Moby Dick is struck and killed...
你们也会有自己那一份的
on that day, you shall have my share.
到那一天，我那一份也是你们的
My 10% of the profits...
这次航行10%的利润
of this entire voyage.
是属于我的
Aye!
是的！
Gold will pour out of Moby Dick's wounds
into your hands.
黄金会从莫比-迪克的伤口里流出来，流到你的手里。
Every drop of his blood...
他的每一滴血
another Spanish doubloon!
都是一枚达布隆金币！
What say you to that, men?
你们觉得怎么样，伙计们？
Sing out!
大声告诉我！
They're all dumfounded, sir, and so am l.
他们都目瞪口呆，长官，我也是。
Hooray for Captain Ahab!
亚哈船长万岁!
Pip, grog all around.
匹普，给所有人倒酒。
A sail, sir, to starboard.
长官，右舷发现一艘船
The Rachel, out of New Bedford.
是瑞秋号，来自新贝德福德。
Captain Gardiner's ship.
She's coming around.
嘉丁纳船长的船。她要过来了。
Captain Ahab,
have you seen a whaleboat adrift?
亚哈船长,你看见过一艘漂流的捕鲸小艇吗?
I've seen nothing.
我什么也没看见
You've seen the white whale?
你见过那只白鲸吗?
We harpooned him
not 10 miles from this spot.
我们刺中了他 离这里不到10英里。
Not dead.
还没有死
-You didn't kill him? 你没杀了他？
-No. 没有
We lost a boat, towed out of sight by him.
To ruin.
我们有一艘小艇被他拖走了，不见行踪
Three days and nights we've searched.
My boy was in it.
我们已经找了三天三夜了。
我儿子在里面。
My own son. Twelve years old.
我的亲生儿子，12岁了
Captain Ahab, will you help me search?
亚哈船长，你肯帮我找找吗?
As we are Christians,
we cannot refuse this man.
既然我们是基督徒，我们不能拒绝这个人。
You will. I know you will help!
你会的，我知道你会帮忙的！
You must!
你一定得帮我！
You must,
and you shall do this thing for me!
你一定要帮我，你应该帮我这个忙！
If thee say no, we'll be in black disgrace.
如果你说不的话，我们就丢脸了。
At home, they'll spit
at the mention of the Pequod's name.
回到家乡，他们都会唾弃"裴廓德号"的名字。
Captain Ahab, answer me!
亚哈船长，回答我!
Captain Gardiner...
嘉丁纳队长……
I seek the white whale!
我要找白鲸!
Your own son's murderer!
杀死你亲生儿子的凶手!
I am losing time.
我没时间了。
Time? I've lost my whole world!
时间吗?我失去了我的整个世界!
I will not go.
I will follow till you say aye to me.
我不会离开。
我会一直跟着你，直到你答应为止。
Run, men. Stand by to lower.
快去，伙计们，准备下船
I am coming over, Captain.
我来了，船长。
Avast! Touch not a rope! I must go.
停住! 别碰绳子! 我必须走了。
Goodbye, I say, and fare thee well.
再见，我说，再见吧。
God help you, Captain Gardiner!
愿上帝保佑你，嘉丁纳船长!
God forgive you, Captain Ahab.
愿上帝饶恕你，亚哈船长。
Stoke up the tryworks.
给炼油炉加满燃料
We shall run forward laden with fire...
我们将要带着满载的火力前进……
to render the white whale's flesh
into unholy oil.
把白鲸的肉炼成罪恶的油。
Blacksmith...
铁匠
I set ye a task.
我给你一个任务
Take these harpoons and lances.
Melt them down.
把这些鱼叉和长矛拿去回炉
Forge me new weapons...
给我打造些新的武器
that will strike deep and hold fast.
要可以刺得很深，牢牢抓住。
Nut do not douse them in water.
但是不要把他们沾到水
They must have a proper baptism.
他们必须接受适当的洗礼。
What say ye, all ye men?
伙计们，你们要说什么？
Will you give as much blood
as shall be needed to temper the steel?
你们愿意付出足够多的鲜血来磨炼钢铁吗?
Aye!
是的！
To my anger, now add your own.
将你们的愤怒附加到我那一份之上
You be the cogs that fit my wheel...
你们是我车轮上的齿轮……
the gunpowder that takes my torch.
点燃我的火把的火药
Pledge yourselves heart...
用你们的心
soul...
你们的灵魂
body...
你们的躯体
-life and lung-- 你们的生命和呼吸来起誓
-Aye, sir. -- 是，长官
...as I pledge myself.
和我一起发誓
Death to Moby Dick.
杀死莫比迪克
Death.
杀
Up helm!
使船向风！
Bring the wind aft!
把风吹到船尾!
Hold it!
等等
Sir, shall I shorten sail?
先生，我要收帆吗?
No. She runs well enough.
不。船速很好
Weather main brace!
打开主转桁索!
Weather yards!
打开帆桁!
The braces, men! Haul away!
转桁索，伙计们，拉开！
Haul away! Lay on your backs and haul!
拉开！躺倒了往后拉！
Earn your salt!
全靠你们自己了！
By all that's holy, Captain!
天哪，船长!
We'll lose every inch of canvas
if we don't ease the ship!
如果我们不让船减速，我们所有的帆布都会被刮跑的。
Mr. Starbuck...
斯达巴克 先生
we're three days behind Moby Dick!
我们比莫比迪克落后了3天的路程
This wind is heaven-sent.
这风是天赐的。
Heaven-sent to destroy us.
上天派来毁灭我们的。
Cut away those rags!
把那些破布剪掉!
Get new canvas aloft!
升起新的帆布！
All hands, tend sails!
全体船员，收帆!
Aye, aye, sir.
是，是，长官
Get aloft.
把帆升起来
They'll trammel under!
他们在下面会挡住帆的！
Aloft with ye! Aloft!
你们都上去，上去！
Get up there! Get aloft!
爬到上面去，把帆升起来！
Captain, we cannot get more canvas up
in this wind!
船长，在这么大的风里，我们不能再增加帆了!
We must!
我们必须这么做
She won't come up!
这行不通的！
The masts!
桅杆！
Cut them away! Cut!
把他们砍断，砍断！
It's away with the masts, or we capsize!
要不把桅杆砍断，我们就要翻船了!
The masts! Cut the masts!
桅杆，切断桅杆！
Let fall.
放下
Let fall, I say.
我说，放下
I'll run you through.
我要把你扎个透心凉
St. Elmo's fire!
圣艾尔摩之火
Have mercy on us!
可怜可怜我们吧!
Aye, men!
是的，伙计们!
Mark it well.
好好记住
It lights our way to the white whale!
它照亮了我们通向莫比迪克的路!
Thus I put out...
就这样我放下了
the last fear.
最后的恐惧
Clear away!
收拾干净！
Raise new sail! We're running on!
升起新的帆布！ 我们继续前进！
Jump, my hearties! Jump now!
行动，我的伙伴们，立刻行动！
Where are the crew of the Pequod?
"裴廓德号"的船员在哪里?
There is not one face I know among 30.
30个人里没有一个人我还能认得出
He has snatched their souls.
他夺走了他们的灵魂。
Look at them. They are gloves.
看看他们。他们是傀儡
Ahab fills them. Ahab moves them.
亚哈支配它们。亚哈操纵它们。
You must admit, Mr. Starbuck,
he called that typhoon's bluff.
你得承认，斯达巴克先生
他接受了台风的挑战
Stood toe-to-toe with the bully,
traded blows with it till it hollered, "Help! "
和那恶霸面对面站着，互相痛殴，直到它大叫:“救命啊!”
Aye, man. And did you see
how he grabbed St. Elmo's fire by the tail?
啊,老兄。你看到他是怎么抓住圣埃尔莫之火的吗?
Only Ahab would do that.
只有亚哈才会那样做。
I see how madmen beget more madmen.
我看到疯子如何催生出更多的疯子。
Yet could I cure their madness now?
然而，我现在能治愈他们的疯狂吗?
Great God, where art thou?
伟大的上帝，你在哪里?
Shall l?
我可以吗？
Heave up!
起锚！
Avast!
停！
It's a mild day, Starbuck.
那是在风和日丽的一天，斯达巴克
Mild-looking sky.
天色看着很好
On such a day, I struck my first whale.
在那样的一天，我捕到了我的第一条鲸鱼。
A boy harpooneer. Forty, aye.
一个少年鱼叉手，四十年，是啊
Forty years and a thousand lowerings ago.
四十年过去了，我也上千次下到小艇里
Why this madness of the chase...
为什么这种疯狂的追逐…
this boiling blood and smoking brow?
这沸腾的血和冒烟的眉毛?
Why palsy the arm at the oar,
the iron, and the lance?
为什么要用桨、铁和长矛把胳膊累到瘫痪呢?
I feel old, Starbuck, and bowed.
我觉得自己老了，斯达巴克，直不起腰来
As though I were Adam...
仿佛我是亚当，
staggering under the piled centuries...
在天堂之后的几百年里
since paradise.
蹒跚前行
Stand close, Starbuck. Close to me.
站近点, 斯达巴克。离我近点。
Let me look into a human eye.
让我看看人类的眼睛。
It is better than to gaze into sea or sky.
它比凝视大海或天空要好。
Captain, now for the last time, I ask thee,
I implore thee...
船长，我最后一次问你，
我恳求你……
Iet us fly these deadly waters.
Let us home.
让我们离开这片危险的水域，我们回家吧
Have they not such mild blue days
even as this in old New Bedford?
即使在以前的新贝德福德，天气也不像现在这样好吗?
What is it?
究竟是什么？
What nameless, inscrutable,
unearthly thing...
什么无名、神秘、不可思议的东西……
commands me against all human lovings
and longings...
命令我去对抗所有人类的爱和渴望……
to keep pushing and crowding
and jamming myself on all the time...
不停地推呀挤呀，把自己塞得满满的……
making me do
what in my own natural heart...
让我去做那些依我的本性
I dare not dream of doing?
做梦都不敢去做的事情?
Is Ahab, Ahab?
亚哈还是那个亚哈吗？
Is it l, God, or who...
是我，上帝，还是谁…
that lifts this arm?
举起的这条胳膊
But if the great sun cannot move...
但是如果没有神那不可见的力量
except by God's invisible power...
连太阳都动不了的话
how can my small heart beat...
我的小心脏怎么能跳动……
my brain think thoughts...
我的大脑怎么会思考……
unless God does that beating,
does that thinking...
除非是神让心跳动，让大脑思考……
does that living...
让我活着
and not l?
而不是
By heavens, man...
伙计，是上天
we are turned round and round
in this world...
让我们在这世界上兜兜转转
Like yonder windlass...
就像那个绞盘一样……
and fate is the handspike.
而命运就是那根绞盘棒。
And all the time, that smiling sky...
一直以来，那微笑的天空……
and this unsounded sea.
这片寂静的大海。
Look ye into its deeps...
看看它的深处……
and see the everlasting slaughter
that goes on.
看那永无休止的杀戮。
Who put it into its creatures
to chase and fang one another?
是谁把它放进它自己的造物里，让它们互相追逐撕咬?
Where do murderers go, man?
杀人犯们都去哪了，伙计?
Who's to doom...
当法官自己被拖到律师面前时，
when the judge himself
is dragged before the bar?
谁会倒霉呢?
But it is a mild day...
但这是个风和日丽的日子
and a mild-looking sky.
天色看着很好
What ails you, Starbuck?
你怎么了，斯达巴克
Why do you tremble so?
你为什么抖得这么厉害?
Because I do not have the bowels
to slaughter thee...
因为我不忍心杀了你……
and save the whole ship's company
from being dragged to doom.
这样可以拯救整艘船的同伴，使他们免于被拖入厄运。
I plainly see my miserable office:
在反抗的过程中，我清楚地看到我那悲惨的职责:
to obey, rebelling.
服从
Worse still, to help thee
to thine impious end.
更糟的是，帮助你达到你那不虔诚的目的。
Starbuck, ye are tied to me.
斯达巴克，你和我是绑在一起的
This act is immutably decreed.
这项法令是不可更改的。
It was rehearsed by ye and me...
在一百万年前大海还没有形成的时候，
a billion years before this ocean rolled.
我和你就已经演练过了。
The air.
在空气里
Do you smell it, lads,
what the wind carries?
你们闻到了吗，伙计们，风里面夹杂的味道?
It smells like land.
像是陆地的味道
-Like an island. 像是一座岛
-Aye. 是的
A coral reef, green moss, shells...
珊瑚礁、青苔、贝壳……
bits and pieces
from all the oceans he ever swam through.
他游过的所有海洋的碎片。
An island to himself is the white whale.
白鲸就是一座独属于他自己的岛屿
Elijah.
以利亚
What say you, lad?
你说呢，小伙子?
The day we sailed, a man....
我们航行的那天，一个男人……
Elijah, his name was.
他的名字叫以利亚
-Well? 什么？
-He said.... 他说
He said, "A day will come at sea...
他说 “在海上，总有一天
"when you smell land
where there be no land.
“你会在没有陆地的地方闻到陆地的气味
"And on that day,
Ahab will go to his grave.
到那日，亚哈必死
"But he will rise again and beckon.
但他会再次起身并且招手
"And then all...
然后所有的人，
"all, save one, shall follow."
除了一个之外，都将追随他的命运
There she blows!
鲸鱼喷水！
Look.
看啊
Mastheaders, the birds mark the place.
桅顶岗哨，
Watch the birds!
注意海鸟！
Helmsman, luff a point.
舵手，转舵。
Stand by the boats!
小艇待命！
Down topgallants!
放下上桅帆!
-Same old bet, Stubb? 还是老的赌注，斯塔布？
-Aye. 好的
No, Pip. Stay on board.
不,皮普。呆在船上。
You be captain in my absence.
Stand ye there on the deck in my place.
我不在时你当队长。你站到甲板上我的位置那里。
Lower away!
放下小艇！
I'm Captain Pip.
我是皮普船长
Did you see him, men?
你们看见他了吗，伙计们?
Did you see his hump?
Like a great snow hill.
你看到他的驼峰了吗?像一座巨大的雪山。
Did you see the way he slides along?
你看到他滑行的样子了吗?
There's majesty for you.
这就是你的威严。
Don't look.
别看
I'll look for you.
我去找你
Did you see the lances in his back?
你看到他背上的长矛了吗?
My lances.
我的长矛
Mine.
我的
Struck in him years ago.
很多年前扎上去的
That's my lads.
这就对了，小伙子们
Wrack the oars off.
把桨拧下来。
Lay into it.
躺进去
Pull there, boys!
划到那里去，孩子们！
Pull, you green-faced posies!
划呀，你们这些晕船的娘炮！
Long and strong, men.
用力划到底，伙计们
Shake your bones, men.
抖擞精神，伙计们
Break in two.
分成两队
Moby Dick, show your trump.
莫比迪克，拿出你的真本事吧
Blister your lungs!
涨破你的肺！
We'll dam off your blood for ye!
我们要为你止血！
Pull soft now.
现在慢点划
He's sounded.
他听见了
Ship oars.
收桨
Rise now, ye white whale.
出来吧，你这白鲸。
Show us your crooked jaw.
让我们看看你弯曲的下巴。
Show us your wrinkled brow.
让我们看看你皱起的额头。
Rise.
出来吧
Those birds.
那些 海鸟
He rises!
他出来了！
In!
靠近！
In and after him!
靠近追上他！
Ride!
爬上去！
Pull in!
靠近!
Let the men go!
别管那些人！
Pull in, men! Closer!
靠近一点，伙计们！ 近一点
He'll not escape!
他逃不掉了！
Thunder in hell! What's wrong with ye?
地狱的雷电! 你怎么了?
Damn ye!
该死的!
Ye whale! Ye damned whale!
你这鲸鱼，你这该死的鲸鱼！
From hell's heart I stab at thee!
我从地狱之心向你刺去!
For hate's sake...
为了仇恨……
I spit my last breath at thee...
我向你吐尽最后一口气……
thou damned whale!
你这该死的鲸鱼!
Away, no more of this.
Back to the Pequod. No more of this.
别再这样了。回到"裴廓德号"。别再这样了。
You see? Do you see?
你看到了吗？你看到了吗？
Ahab beckons.
亚哈招手了
He's dead, but he beckons.
他死了，但他在招手。
In after him!
靠近追上他！
After him!
追上他！
After that devil?
追那个魔鬼？
Moby Dick's no devil. He's a whale.
莫比迪克不是魔鬼，他是一只鲸鱼
A monstrous big whale, aye,
but a whale, no more.
一只巨大的鲸鱼，是的，但也就是只鲸鱼而已。
And we're whaling men, no less.
我们也依然是捕鲸人。
We do not turn from whales. We kill them.
我们不会从鲸鱼面前逃走，我们要杀了他们
We'll kill Moby Dick!
我们要杀了莫比迪克!
Pull!
划啊！
Ye heard Mr. Starbuck, didn't ye?
你听见斯达巴克先生了吧？
Didn't ye?
听见了吗？
Be ye whaling men or no?
你们是捕鲸人吗？
Pull, ye sheep-heads. Pull!
划啊，你们这些蠢货，划啊！
Ye should not have come back,
ye grinning whale.
你不应该回来的，你这露齿狞笑的鲸鱼。
We're cutting new mouths
in ye to grin with.
我们给你切个新的嘴巴出来，让你笑
The coffin.
那口棺材
Drowned Queequeg's coffin
was my life buoy.
淹死的魁魁格的棺材是我的救生圈
For one whole day and night...
整整一天一夜
it sustained me
on that soft and dirge-like main.
它支撑着我在那柔软的、像挽歌一样的大海上航行。
Then a sail appeared.
然后出现了一艘船
It was the Rachel.
是瑞秋号
The Rachel,
who in her long melancholy search...
瑞秋号在寻找她失踪的孩子
for her missing children found...
那漫长而忧郁的过程中，
another orphan.
又找到了一个孤儿
The drama 's done.
戏演完了
All are departed away.
所有的人都走了。
The great shroud of the sea...
"裴廓德号"和它的船员们
rolls over the Pequod, her crew...
还有莫比迪克
and Moby Dick.
都被大海那巨大的裹尸布卷走了
I only am escaped, alone...
只有我一个人逃出来
to tell thee.
给你们讲这个故事
原创翻译：egg
版权所有：12841692@qq.com